A Guide to the J. L. Blair Buck Papers 1958-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The J. L. Blair Buck Papers 1958-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7783-a
This collection consists of ca. 1350 items in five five-inch grey Hollinger boxes (two shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was obtained on 28 June 1972, as a gift from Mrs. J. L. B Buck of Richmond.
Scope and Content Information
These papers comprise the working records of the Virginia Committee for Public Schools in the years of massive resistance to public school integration, 1958-1960. From its headquaters in Richmond, this committee acted to influence public debate and state legislation toward public schools and to coordinate the activities of numerous local committees. The committee was directed from its inception by Dr. J.L. Blair Buck of Richmond, (1886-[1967]), who until his retirement in 1956 had been Coordinator of Teacher Education for the Virginia State Department of Education. The committee was formally dissolved in 1960, upon the evident failure of massive resistance as a program.
The Buck colelction bears upon a number of related institutions during this period. Among them are the following: Gray Commission, 1955; Perow Commission, 1959; Virginia Society for the Preservation of Public Education, 1955; Virginia Council on Human Relations; Southern Regional Council; NAACP; and Defenders of State Sovereignty and Individual Liberties.
Committee correspondents include: J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.; Warren Cox; Virginius Dabney; Ted Dalton; Colgate W. Darden; John Fitzgerald; Hugh M. Gordon; Earl E. Hall; Harrison Mann; Minor C. Miller; Francis Pickens Miller; Lorin A. Thompson; and Robert Whitehead.
Arrangement
When acquired, the papers were foldered roughly according to subject, in no particular chronological order. It was thought best to preserve as much as possible the existing subject titles, but at the same time to make the collection more accessible by establishing a chronology.
Contents List
- Committee correspondence Jan. 1959-Nov. 1960, 16 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1959 (Box 2)
  re. local committees: Alexandria, Arlington, Blacksburg, Charlottesville, Christiansburg, Colleges, Fairfax-Falls Church, Lynchburg, Norfolk, Peninsula, Prince Edward County, Radford, Richmond Area, Roanok, Rockingham County, Warren County, Washington County, Waynesboro, Williamsburg
- Miscellaneous statements, forms, articles, and pamphlets 1959 (Box 2)
  Re. public schools and state legislation
- Historical sketches of the Committee by W.M. Lightsey and J.L.B> Buck 1959 (Box 3)
- Minutes, agendas, of steering committee - executive board meetings Nov. 1958-Oct. 1959 (Box 3)
- Legal affairs of Committee 1959 (Box 3)
- Accounts of finance committee 1959 (Box 3)
- Correspondence on taxes, withholding 1959-1960 (Box 3)
- Audit, Virginia Committee, correspondence re. same 1960 (Box 3)
- Spiral date book of J.L.B. Buck Feb-Mar 1959 (Box 3)
- Invoices, Virginia Committee 1958-1960 (Box 4)
- Bank statements, Virginia Committee 1958-1960 (Box 4)
- Expenses, W.M. Lightsey 1959-1960 (Box 4)
- Spiral postage and misc. expense book 1959-1960 (Box 4)
- Bank Deposit book, seven deposit slips, Virginia Committee 1958-1960 (Box 4)
- Check stubs, Virginia committee 1958-1960 (Box 4)
- Cash receipt book, Virginia Committee 1958-1960 (Box 4)
- Three rubber stamps, Virginia Committee (Box 4)
- AMs for 1931 article by J.L.B. Buck, Gravel in the Shoe, or 'I Know the Negro'1931 (Box 4)
- Race relations miscellany 1949-1960 (Box 5)